I’m not an urban planner,
but I play one on TV.
So you might ask,
“Why do you run a
YouTube channel about"
"urban planning and
walkable cities then?”
And I would say,
"What a coincidence!"
"That’s the topic of this video.”
I grew up in a car-dependent,
car-infested city called London.
To avoid confusion on this channel,
I usually refer to it as
“Fake London”, or
sometimes something derogatory.
By the time I was a teenager,
I was pretty bored of Fake London,
so I wanted to get out
as quickly as possible
and see the rest of the world.
So while I was in university,
I took advantage of internships
to live in several different
cities in Ontario,
as well as in the
San Francisco Bay Area.
During this time,
I also drove across the
United States 7 times,
and across Canada once.
And I stayed in dozens of
cities and towns along the way.
Apart from some minor differences,
all of these places
were pretty similar.
There’s an overwhelming sameness
between almost all cities
in the U.S. and Canada,
primarily due to their
car-centric design.
In the end,
I decided to live in
downtown Toronto.
This was a place that
was interesting to me,
but I didn’t really
know why at the time.
I just knew I liked it a lot
more than suburbia.
Incidentally,
when I lived in downtown Toronto,
I was able to easily live car-free,
and this allowed me to save
a huge amount of money
when I was young.
After the dot-com crash of 2000,
"Pets.com."
"Because pets can’t drive!"
"Oh, yeah!"
"Ooh, this is my kind of party."
I was laid off from my
first job out of school,
and I was left unemployed
for a very long time.
When I finally did find a job,
it was at a significantly lower salary
than what I was earning before.
There’s simply no way I could have
gotten through that time in my life
if I had to own a car to buy food,
to apply for
unemployment benefits,
to go to job interviews,
and to go to work.
This is one of the reasons
why I am so hostile
towards car-dependent places.
Because they are
burdening everyone
with thousands of dollars per year
for the costs of an automobile,
just so that they can work
and feed themselves.
This is fundamentally wrong.
Nobody should have to own a car,
just to participate in society.
And designing a city
that way on purpose
is criminal.
But what really opened my eyes
is when I got a job that
required me to travel.
Suddenly I was being sent to
the U.K.,
Germany,
Taiwan,
Japan, and
all over the United States.
I started realizing that there was a
whole world of interesting
cities out there,
and they weren’t all the same
car-centric sprawl of the GTA
or the Bay Area.
During this time,
I travelled excessively,
for both personal and business trips.
There was a period of
several years where
I wasn't in the same time zone for
more than about 3 weeks at a time.
One thing this insane amount
of travel did provide me with,
was the opportunity to see
how other people lived
all over the world.
I wasn’t going places as a tourist,
I was going to where people
actually lived and worked.
I was taking local trains in Tokyo,
I was stuck in rush-hour
traffic in Boston,
I was taking the S-Bahn in Berlin,
I was taking taxis to remote
factories in Shenzhen.
And I was going between these
drastically different cities
on a nearly weekly basis.
It was amazing to me to see
how different all of these cities were,
and the different ways
that people lived,
but at the time I never
really thought about
why this was the case.
Like most people,
I assumed it was for
cultural reasons, or
due to the weather
and local environment,
because I was completely
ignorant about urban planning.
That all changed
during a trip to Houston.
I was in the middle of an
around-the-world trip.
These are discounted tickets for
travelling to multiple cities,
but you need to travel only
in one global direction
(always East,)
(or always West)
until you’ve flown
all the way around the world.
For most of my trip, I had taken
public transportation in
the cities I had visited,
but I had been to Houston
many times before, and I knew
I needed to rent a car.
However, I had met up with some
coworkers for this leg of the journey,
so we shared one car
between the three of us.
We had a day off on Sunday, and
my coworkers had taken the car.
When I was unpacking
in my hotel room,
I noticed that my suitcase
was falling apart,
so I searched for a
luggage shop nearby.
Thankfully, there was
one 800 meters away.
No problem!
I decided to walk there.
That, was a terrible,
terrible mistake.
I exited the hotel to find that
it was on a street with no sidewalks.
None at all.
So I crossed through
the adjacent parking lots.
It is disturbingly common to find
places without any sidewalks
in American suburbia,
but I had grown up
in a car-infested city
so I was used to it.
As I got out to the main road,
there was a sidewalk.
I didn’t know it at the time,
but this road was what
Strong Towns refers to as a 'stroad':
a street that is designed like a road,
and in doing so, is expensive,
inefficient,
and dangerous.
This walk was pretty uncomfortable.
The weather was nice,
but there were no trees
to provide any shade.
The landscape was boring and
I was surrounded by asphalt.
All of the businesses I passed
were far in the distance,
behind giant parking lots,
and the signs were all oversized,
and only meant to be
read while driving.
In a place like this,
you’re walking next to polluted air
and the constant noise
from high-speed vehicles.
And you always need to be alert
for any cars going in
and out of driveways,
as drivers are only looking
at oncoming traffic,
they are not looking for pedestrians.
And in America,
people will blame you
if you’re hit by a car.
Stoplights are long and
there are too many of them.
And because cars can turn right
on red lights in America,
you have to be hyper-aware
when crossing the stroad.
This is the kind of
pedestrian experience
that people who
never walk anywhere
think is acceptable.
But then I got to this spot
and the sidewalk just…
ended.
No warning.
No alternative.
It was just... gone.
But there was a well-trodden
path through the grass,
so I followed it to
this bridge,
where there was...
nothing.
As I shimmied along the curb
next to the guardrail,
with high-speed cars and
trucks passing by me,
I thought about how
ridiculous this was.
I was balancing on a
few centimeters of curb
while crossing a 28-metre bridge
with 7 lanes of car traffic.
There was no consideration given
to anybody who wasn’t in a car,
and there was no other alternative
for people walking.
At that moment, I decided that,
if I lived through this walk,
I wanted to live in a place
that was the exact opposite
of a place like this.
When I made it to the other side,
there was also no sidewalk, of course.
And I crossed through
some more parking lots
to get to the luggage shop.
Needless to say,
I took a cab back to the hotel.
Yeah.
I took a taxi,
to go 800 meters.
In the United States,
over 45% of car trips
are 3 miles or less.
Less than 5 kilometers.
That’s insane.
Europeans assume
Americans drive everywhere
because "they’re fat and lazy",
but it’s not.
It’s because these trips simply
can’t be done any other way.
When I got back to my hotel,
I started reading about
how cities were designed.
I learned about car-dependency
and I learned about walkability.
And I learned about how these
places have changed over time,
and how some places have
designed their cities for humans,
not just for motor vehicles.
One of the things
that really upset me
is that the desolate
asphalt-covered cities
I had visited in the U.S. and Canada
weren’t always this way.
I was told that these
cities were like this
because they were
“designed for the car".
That’s not true.
They weren't designed for the car,
they were bulldozed for the car.
Look at these pictures of my
hometown of Fake London.
This city
is beautiful.
Now it looks like this.
This is a picture of
Houston in the 1970s.
No, it wasn’t bombed.
They did this to themselves.
This used to be a
compact, walkable city
that was just as good as
those in Europe or Asia.
And they destroyed it.
When you see a place like this,
you think the developers must
have got away with something,
but literally everything you see,
right down to the colour of the paint
of the lines in the parking lot,
are defined in some
book of regulations.
And those regulations are
overwhelmingly designed
to make places that
are only accessible
by car.
This is entirely by design,
and it’s entirely by choice.
It didn’t need to be this way,
and it doesn’t need to stay this way.
And THAT is why I became interested
in urban planning.
My walk in Houston was
not the first or the last
terrible experience I would have
walking in an American city,
but it was the most memorable.
And I have absolutely zero
patience for apologists
for this kind of car-centric,
anti-human design.
I clearly wasn’t
the only person who
had ever walked here,
as proven by the path in the grass.
You can see people walking
here on Google Street View.
In a place like this,
if you’re too poor to drive a car,
then you’re literally forgotten about.
And this situation hasn’t
changed at all in the last decade,
which is why I was able
to get this video of it.
There’s no excuse for this.
If you have enough room
for 7 lanes of car traffic,
then you have enough
room for a sidewalk,
or a bicycle path.
This is what a 28-metre
bridge looks like
in Amsterdam.
It has a sidewalk,
and a two-way bicycle path
on both sides of the road.
And yeah,
this area in Houston
is very suburban;
almost 30 kilometers
from the city center,
but that’s no excuse.
The area is lined with
businesses and shops,
many of which are staffed
by minimum-wage workers.
In America,
housing prices are talked about a lot,
but the most important metric
is housing PLUS
transportation costs.
How are these employees
supposed to get to work?
Do they all need to drive?
Can they even afford to do that?
Here’s what an industrial park
in the middle of nowhere
looks like in the Netherlands.
The street is only 2 lanes wide,
and there’s a beautiful
two-way cycling path
that can be used for people
walking and cycling.
North Americans balk at designing
pedestrian and
cycling infrastructure
anywhere but in busy downtowns.
But here,
employees of the nearby
factories and warehouses
can use these safe paths
to get to and from work,
and for other trips like
going for lunch, too.
There is always a long list
of excuses people make
as to why nobody walks or
cycles in North America.
But that’s what they are:
excuses.
The real reason is that
it’s not enjoyable,
comfortable, or safe
to walk or cycle
in a place like this.
Yeah, the weather
is bad sometimes,
or there might be hills,
but don’t you think that this guy
would appreciate a sidewalk?
Houston is one of the worst
examples of urban sprawl.
For my Dutch viewers,
if Amsterdam were as
sprawling as Houston,
then a circle including
Alkmaar,
Leiden,
Utrecht,
and Lelystad
would all be connected by
continuous car-dependent sprawl.
There is a right way
and a wrong way to design a city,
and this is decidedly the wrong way,
for so many reasons.
And by the way,
the barbeque joints
in Houston are good,
but the best brisket
I ever had in my life
was at Mighty Quinn’s.
And you know where
that restaurant is?
New York City.
"New York City!?"
"Get a rope."
But the sad part is,
Houston is not even the
worst city in the U.S.,
and the city is actually doing
more to change things
than many other U.S. cities.
For example,
Houston recently deployed a
completely new bus network
literally overnight,
and it has led to
significantly higher ridership.
Streetfilms made an excellent
video about these changes.
They’re really great.
Bravo to Houston Metro
for doing this.
Houston has been installing
several bicycle lanes as well.
And the city has removed
minimum parking requirements
for 2 downtown neighbourhoods,
in an attempt to
build a more walkable
mixed-use downtown.
Speaking of mixed-use,
it is a common myth that
Houston does not have zoning.
It’s true that the city does not
have a thing called 'zoning',
but they have lots
of other restrictions,
such as minimum
parking requirements,
minimum lot sizes,
and other regulations that cities would
normally put into their zoning codes.
And they also have city-enforced
deed restrictions that limit
what you can build on
certain parcels of land,
that allows, for example,
only single-family homes to be
built in many neighbourhoods.
In short,
Houston has all of the worst
parts of a zoning ordinance,
they just don’t call it 'zoning'.
City Beautiful has a
great video about this
if you’re interested in learning more.
But despite all the work
that is being done,
Houston has a very, very,
very long way to go.
The city recently completed
a multimillion-dollar project
that is called a “protected
intersection for pedestrians".
Does this look
pedestrian-friendly to you?
It is the intersection of
two 6-lane stroads,
and it literally has high-speed
slip lanes for drivers
so that they can bypass the
traffic light when turning right.
Slip lanes are insanely
dangerous for people walking.
It’s absolutely ridiculous
that engineers would
purposefully design slip lanes
in a place that’s supposedly
meant for pedestrians,
and being billed as
"pedestrian-friendly".
I mean, I guess it’s better
than walking through the grass and
across a death-bridge with no sidewalk?
But come on!
This is what counts as
"pedestrian infrastructure"?
And of course,
Houston is also home
to the Katy freeway,
the widest freeway
in the United States.
In 2011,
2.2 billion dollars was spent
widening the highway
to over 20 lanes,
and as a result,
travel times out of
downtown have increased
by up to 30%.
This is a massive sum of money
that could have been better
spent on public transit
or other alternatives to driving
that are proven to reduce car traffic,
but instead it was used as an
expensive demonstration
of induced demand.
And no lessons have
been learned here.
The city and state are
planning an additional
7 billion dollars on
highway expansion.
This project will demolish
4 religious buildings,
2 schools,
168 homes,
1,067 multifamily units,
and 331 businesses
that employ almost 25,000 people.
It is literally
never-ending.
It’s often said that
the truth about a city’s aspirations
isn’t found in its vision,
it’s found in its budget.
So despite the millions spent
on pedestrian improvements
that somehow also include
faster turning lanes for drivers,
Houston is spending billions
on car infrastructure,
and is fully addicted
to car-dependency.
I just... don’t know how
you undo the damage
caused by a place
designed like this.
How does this ever
become sustainable?
Financially or environmentally?
And to me, the most sad part
is that people who have grown up
only knowing car dependence
don’t see a problem with this.
To them, restricting cars is
literally taking away their freedom,
because they have become
so addicted to car-dependency
that they are incapable
of understanding
that it is possible to
design places where,
not only do you not need to drive,
you won’t even want to drive,
and that lifestyle can be better
in almost every way.
My travels gave me
the opportunity to visit
every major city in
the United States,
most of them multiple times.
And as a result,
I have absolutely no desire
to go back to any of them.
But those experiences shaped
the way I think about cities,
and they're what ultimately
resulted in our family
moving to the Netherlands,
the country that has the
best cities in the world.
And hey,
if Houston weren’t so terrible,
we never would have this
YouTube channel, so...
thanks, Houston!
I owe you one.
I’d like to thank my
supporters on Patreon,
who pay me to relive
the bad ol’ days.
If you’d like to support the channel,
and get access to bonus videos,
visit Patreon.com/notjustbikes.