JASON (voiceover): I grew up in
a car-infested city called London.
London, Ontario, Canada.
But we don’t want to raise our kids
in an environment like this,
and we moved to Amsterdam instead.
So why is that?
One thing you immediately notice
when coming to the Netherlands is that
there are a lot of children around.
You’ll routinely see even
young children cycling to school,
playing with their friends, and just
hanging out in the city.
The Dutch are famous for having
the happiest kids in the world, and
a big part of that is
the fact that they can
literally have chocolate sprinkles
for breakfast.
But the other big factor
is the level of independence
that children have here.
I got used to seeing children everywhere,
so it was amazing to see the difference
the first time I returned to
my hometown in Canada.
I drove around several
residential neighborhoods, and
while I occasionally saw some
kids in the park with their parents,
I never saw any children
out on their own, and...
that’s really sad.
I’ve talked to some parents
from suburban Canada
about why they don’t let their
children out on their own,
and they usually say,
"Because it’s too dangerous".
One person even said,
"Somebody could come
along with a white van,"
"scoop them up, and
nobody would even notice.”
Now, that’s insane,
because Canada is one of the
safest countries in the world,
and abductions by strangers
are exceedingly unlikely,
so...
why do people think this?
Well, there are various reasons
for this cultural change,
including an increase in
fearmongering media,
but this is an urban planning channel,
so we’re going to talk about the reasons
linked to city design. because...
there are a lot of them.
In her famous book
The Death and Life of
Great American Cities,
Jane Jacobs refers to an effect she calls
“eyes on the street".
Essentially, it means
that people feel safer
to be in places with many
other people, like here,
in this suburb of Amsterdam.
By comparison,
North American-style
car-dependent suburbia
is desolate for people outside of a car.
It’s depressing to walk there,
and I know, because I’ve done it a lot,
in the process of filming these videos.
I’m almost always the
only one out walking,
and I definitely get the feeling that
if something happened to me,
hundreds of people would drive by
without even noticing.
So it shouldn’t be too surprising
that some parents are uncomfortable
having their children walk
in an environment like this.
Now, there’s another
“safety” reason that’s
a bit more rational:
Canadian and American cities
are really dangerous for pedestrians.
While overall traffic fatalities
in developed nations
have generally fallen
steadily since the 1970s,
in the US and Canada,
a big part of this was achieved
by putting almost everyone
inside of a car.
But while people inside
of cars may be safer,
pedestrian deaths have increased
significantly in the past few decades,
due to:
an increase in car traffic,
larger trucks and SUVs,
distracted driving,
and higher vehicle speeds.
Ultimately,
these unsafe roads
ead to a vicious circle:
parents are more likely to
drive their children everywhere
because it’s not safe due to all the cars,
but in doing so, they’re adding
one more car to the problem,
and making it even less safe.
I’d like to point out that
this is a unique problem
caused only by cars.
I mean,
nobody ever kept their kids
from walking to school
just because too many
people took the tram.
But also, it’s impractical for children
to go anywhere on their
own in a place like this.
Suburbia is car-dependent.
That means it’s almost
impossible to get anywhere
without a car.
So even if you wanted your
child to walk somewhere,
they simply... can’t.
It’s either too far,
or it's not feasible, because
of a lack of sidewalks.
When I have discussions with
people from my suburban
hellscape of a hometown,
they usually agree that the city is quiet
and soul-crushingly boring,
but they will inevitably say,
“But it’s a good place to raise children.”
I completely disagree.
Suburbia might be a good
place to shelter toddlers,
but as soon as a child is
more than about 6 years old,
being trapped in a McMansion
on the edge of town
seriously inhibits their
growth and independence.
They might be able to
walk to a friend’s house,
if they’re lucky enough to live
somewhere with a sidewalk.
But they’re unlikely to be
able to walk to school,
or anywhere else for that matter.
In the Netherlands,
60% of children walk or cycle to school,
compared to 28% in Canada,
mostly those kids who
live in the few remaining
walkable pre-war neighborhoods
that would be illegal to build today
due to modern zoning.
But when I was a kid,
that number was 58% in Canada,
almost identical to the Netherlands today.
Look at these Canadian kids
walking to their rural
school in the 1920s,
through the snow,
uphill both ways.
Yeah,
that never happens anymore.
This is the bicycle parking lot of a
typical middle school in Amsterdam.
And this is the bicycle parking lot
of an elementary school.
It is obvious here that
the majority of children
arrive on their own bicycles.
I’m constantly hearing excuses
from North Americans
as to why kids can walk or cycle
to school in the Netherlands
but not in Canada,
and it’s usually some nonsense
about the weather or the hills.
Do either of those things
explain the massive drop in
the number of kids walking
to school in Canada?
Did Canada’s weather get
worse in the past 40 years?
Did the hills get higher?
No, of course not.
But we did stop building
family-friendly housing
anywhere that wasn’t car-dependent.
Meanwhile, here in the Netherlands,
it’s not just kids in cities
who cycle to school, it's...
everywhere.
BicycleDutch has several videos showing
dozens of children cycling
long distances to school
in suburbs, towns, and villages.
And it’s more than just school, too.
Kids have lots of sports
and other activities,
so in the Netherlands,
it’s very common to see
children walking or cycling
while dressed in
football gear,
(not that kind of football)
or hockey gear,
(not that kind of hockey)
because they travel to all these
activities by themselves.
In the US and Canada,
you have the stereotype of the suburban
'soccer mom',
the mother who spends all her time
shuttling her kids around
from school to activities
to playdates and back.
Because,
until a kid is about 16 years old
and has their own driver’s license,
they need to be driven around
everywhere by their parents,
and...
this is considered
“normal”.
Is it any surprise that
kids in the U.S. and Canada
don’t get enough exercise?
But I can’t blame them
for wanting to stay inside
playing video games all day,
when
outside looks like this.
These problems originate
in car-dependent suburbs,
but unfortunately,
decades of suburbanization
have changed the overall culture,
where now many Canadians
don’t believe it’s safe for any
children to be out on their own.
So even if you could afford to live in
one of the very few remaining
walkable neighbourhoods,
you still can’t give your children
the independence they deserve.
For example, here in Amsterdam,
we started allowing our children
to go to the park without us
when they were 9 and 6 years old.
This is totally normal and
accepted in the Netherlands.
If we let our children do this in Canada,
we would literally have
someone call the police.
Or worse.
Now, you might think I’m exaggerating,
but there are stories about this happening
all over the U.S. and Canada,
and the one that angered me the most,
was the story of Adrian Crook.
Adrian is a father of 5 children,
and lives in downtown Vancouver, Canada.
He has always been a vocal advocate of
allowing kids to have their independence,
and has written about how
walkable urban city design
makes this easier and more practical.
As part of this effort,
Adrian and his kids would ride
the bus to school every day.
He did this with them for two years,
but in 2017,
he started letting them
do it on their own.
A short time later, he was
anonymously reported
to the Ministry of Children
and Family Development.
The whole story is available on
his blog, that I’ll link to below,
but in the end,
the Ministry decided that
children under the age of 10
could not be unsupervised
in or outside of the home,
for any amount of time,
and if Adrian let any of his
children out unsupervised again,
even to go to the store across the street,
his children would be taken away from him.
Adrian literally had to
spend 3 years of his life
suing the Ministry of Children
and Family Development
just to allow his children
to have some independence.
And if you think that’s insane,
in Ontario, the province where I’m from,
children legally can not be
on their own until they're 16,
unless, quote,
“adequate supervision”
is provided.
When I was a kid,
'adequate supervision' was, say,
having the phone number of a neighbor.
But the problem is,
what constitutes “adequate supervision”
is becoming increasingly strict,
and arbitrarily applied.
This article has examples
from all over Canada,
where child welfare investigations
were started because,
for example,
a 9-year-old walked to school on her own,
or because a mother allowed
her children to play in
the fenced backyard of their own house,
while she was watching them from inside.
Now, you might say that these
visits from police or social
workers are just overreactions,
and it’s better to be safe than sorry.
But these social workers have the power to
literally take your
children away from you.
You’re crazy if you don’t think
this has a chilling effect
that ultimately limits the independence
of children in North America.
Personally, I have absolutely no interest
in finding out the hard way what the
currently-accepted definition of
“adequate supervision” may be,
when it comes to keeping
custody of my children.
Unfortunately, the solutions to
these problems are not easy,
because they involve changing
not just cultural issues,
but also the fundamental design of
North American cities and suburbs.
Traditional mixed-use
walkable neighbourhoods
have a multitude of benefits,
but walkability is nearly
impossible to retrofit
on top of car-dependent suburbia.
And the last few remaining walkable
places in the US and Canada
are in such high demand,
that they’re completely
unaffordable to most people.
Of course,
we’re also not building any more
walkable places like this in Canada,
because they’re illegal to build,
due to zoning and car-centric regulations,
like minimum parking requirements.
So what was built a
hundred years ago is it.
We’re not getting any more.
And if you can’t afford it,
too bad.
There’s this insane myth in North America
that when you have kids, you need a car,
and you need to live in suburbia,
when the exact opposite is true.
What children really need is fewer cars,
because cars are dangerous,
especially for children.
Plus, news flash:
Kids can’t drive!
But they can walk or cycle, though
only if it’s safe.
Here in the Netherlands,
almost all new neighborhoods are walkable,
and some of them are even car-free.
Unsurprisingly, you see kids
travelling on their own and
playing together in the streets.
So a few years ago,
my wife and I had to make a decision.
What kind of a life did
we want for us and,
more importantly, for our children?
The solution
seemed pretty clear:
we moved to the country with
the happiest kids in the world.
I’d like to take this opportunity to
thank my supporters on Patreon,
who pay me to remake the classics.
If you'd like to join them in
supporting this channel,
visit patreon.com/notjustbikes.